对于航天工业中成千上万的科学家和工程师的命运啊
For all the knowledge of the thousands of scientists and engineers in the space industry,
当然要靠自我的奋斗 但也要考虑历史的进程
sometimes the old adage of "The best laid plans of mice of men" can be equally applied to their efforts.
1999年的火星气候探测者号就是这种情况
This was certainly the case of a Mars Climate Orbiter mission of 1999,
这次任务也注定会被钉在人类航天史的耻辱柱上
and this will go down in space history as one of the biggest facepalms to date.
如果你经常逛我的评论区
If you're an avid comment reader,
应该会发现已经有人提到过我经常会在视频里同时使用英制和公制
then you may have seen comments on my videos about why I tend to use both Imperial and metric unit
而不是只使用公制
instead of just metric,
原因简言之就是在美国和英国 许多人仍然使用英制系统
basically the simple answer is that many people in the US and the UK still use the Imperial system,
即使现在科学和工程领域早已把公制作为自己的标准单位制
even though metric is now the de facto measuring system in the science and engineering worlds.
这是件好事 因为人们不会在计算中出现单位混淆的情况
Now this is fine providing that you don't get them mixed up when you're doing your calculations
就像1999年NASA和洛克希德马丁公司的工程师与导航员一样
like the engineers and navigators of Lockheed Martin and NASA did in 1999.
上世纪九十年代末 克林顿政府向NASA施压
In the late 1990s NASA was under pressure by the Clinton administration
希望让太空任务更快 更精巧 更廉价
to make each mission go faster, smaller and cheaper,
于是NASA没有选择专注于一个大项目 而是采取分头行动
so rather than focusing on a single large project, NASA diversified their operations.
光在1999年就进行了
This meant that in 1999
哈勃望远镜的维护任务与国际空间站的建造任务
whilst servicing the Hubble Space Telescope and building the International Space Station,
外加其他三个低开销的连续的火星探测任务
NASA also planned a low-cost program to operate three missions simultaneously on the Red Planet.
“火星勘探98”项目包含一个火星极地着陆器 搭载两个微小火星撞击器
The "Mars Surveyor 98" program featured the Mars Polar Lander with a pair of impact of micro probes on board,
还有一个中继通信卫星——火星气候探测者号(MCO)
and a satellite and communications relay which was the Mars Climate Orbiter.
这个地外探测器原定执行首个火星长期气候探测任务
This extraterrestrial probe, it was hoped,
would conduct the first long-term detailed study of Martian weather.
MCO需要质量很轻
Mars Climate Orbiter had to be low mass
因此只装了一个太阳帆板 在火星可以提供500瓦电力
so it was fitted with a single solar panel rated at 500 watts at Mars.
这种不对称布局使得探测器面向太阳时会被太阳风施加一个旋转力矩
This asymmetrical design meant that the spacecraft was subjected to rotational force
as the panel caught the solar wind.
而探测器可以使用动量轮来修正它
The probe could correct for this using the onboard reaction wheels,
但需要定期用星上肼发动机进行角动量卸载
but these needed to be periodically desaturated or reset using corrective burns from its hydrazine thrusters.
这些常规机动都记录在洛克希德马丁总部的计算机内
These routine maneuvers were recorded in a file on Lockheed-Martin's ground-based computer,
导航员也早已将这些定期修正考虑在内
from which for navigators had calculated periodic course corrections.
然而在九个月的飞行当中
However during the nine month trip
常规的调姿点火却遇到了大问题
regular tiny thruster burns were compounding into a sizeable problem.
正常来讲 洛克希德马丁的合同中规定了
As was customary, Lockheed Martin's contract stipulated that
所有通信内容都要使用公制单位
all communications should use the standard metric units,
所以平常接收到的传感器数据默认都是公制
so in daily sensor readings, all data was assumed to be the metric standard
即牛顿力每秒
of Newton's of force per second.
但因为严重的失误
Unfortunately, there had been a major oversight.
文件中使用的单位是磅力每秒
The files actually contained measurements in pounds of force per second
这是至今仍然在发射时广泛使用的英制单位
using the imperial units which was still widely used in the launch industry at the time.
而 1 磅力 = 4.45 牛顿力
Because one pound force equals 4.45 Newton's force,
导致每次轨道修正都差了整整4.45倍
each of the corrective thruster operations was underestimated by a factor of 4.45,
让探测器进入了错误的轨道
putting the craft into the wrong trajectory.
这事在最开始让NASA喷气推进实验室(JPL)的几个导航员注意到了
These showed up when several navigators at NASA's Jet Propulsion Laboratory or JPL
noticed that something was amiss.
探测器一路上为了保持轨道而进行的修正比预计多了十倍
The probe was making more than ten times as many minor adjustments as planned
as it tried to compensate to keep it on course.
可是这些顾虑最后并没有被正式提交
However, these concerns were never raised formally.
在1999年9月23日
On September 23rd 1999,
MRO预计以140英里(226公里)高度飞越火星
the Mars Climate Orbiter was scheduled to approach the Martian surface
at a distance of a 140 miles, 226 kilometres,
同时进行长时段反推点火 进入火星椭圆轨道
whilst performing a long retrograde burn to enter an elliptical orbit around the Red Planet.
而一天之前 JPL最后一次计算发现探测器可能偏离了轨道
Just one day before arrival, JPL latest calculations indicated that the probe might be off-course,
其会以93英里(150公里)的高度飞越火星
and could approach Mars at an altitude of just 93 miles or 150 kilometers.
项目组开了个会 讨论下能不能临时点火抬一下近火点
The operations team met and discussed the possibility of executing a contingency burn
to raise the trajectory of the probe.
但当时只剩一天来上传数据 执行机动了
But with only a day to upload and carry out this maneuver,
探测器精确位置也不好说 所以最后也没落实下来
and some uncertainty about the precise location of the probe, the burn was never executed.
这样一来小组只能祈祷探测器偏离得别太离谱了
Now the team could only hope that the approach would not be further off-course then calculated.
如果近火点低于53英里(80公里) 探测器就会在火星大气中烧毁
If the probe's altitude dipped below 53 miles or 80 kilometers, it would burn up in the atmosphere.
远在火星那边 MCO 在 UTC 0900 点燃了主发动机
Far from Earth, Mars Climate Orbiter continued its course and at 9 a.m. UTC began its main engine burn.
探测器开始减速 并飞入火星阴影区 暂时失去了通信
The probe decelerated and passed beyond the horizon of Mars out of radio contact.
23分钟后 地面控制团队开始尝试监听信号
23 minutes later, the ground control team listened for a signal,
却什么都没收到
but heard only silence.
MCO再也没发出任何信号 再也没被观测到
The Mars Climate Orbiter was never heard from or seen again,
至今也没有找到任何残骸
and no wreckage has been found to date.
但之后的深入计算发现
But more detailed calculations later indicated
探测器当时一头扎进了距离火星表面只有37英里(60公里)的高空
that its course fell to just 37 miles or 60 kilometers from the surface.
这个高度 它必死无疑
At this altitude, there was no way back.
大气的剧烈摩擦会直接把脆弱的探测器一套带走 死得连渣都没有
The atmospheric friction was far beyond the fragile probes limits, and the orbiter was destroyed.
事故后 他们发表了一份调查报告 现在仍然可以下载到
After the incident, a report was commissioned, which is still available to download and read,
当中怒斥了NASA与合同承包商洛克希德马丁之间缺乏沟通
which criticized the lack of communications within NASA and with the contractor Lockheed Martin,
与任务操作员缺乏训练的问题
and the lack of training for key operatives on the mission.
洛克希德马丁与JPL也从此次失败中吸取了教训
Lockheed Martin and JPL learned from their mistakes.
五年后 两家再次联手研发了火星勘测轨道飞行器(MRO)
5 years later, the two organizations together developed the Mars Reconnaissance Orbiter,
完成了它出师未捷身先死的前辈的多想目标
a mission that accomplished many of the goals of its ill-fated predecessor,
其中的数学计算彻底贯彻了国际通用标准——公制单位
using exclusively the international language of scientific measurement, namely the metric system.
讲道理 MCO并不是因为数学坠毁的
Now technically the probe was not lost because of maths
因为计算时输入的数据本身就是错的 而且是很小儿科的错误
but because the calculations were fed the wrong information, namely good old-fashioned human error.
输入的是垃圾 输出的肯定也是垃圾
It's the old programmer saying of rubbish in rubbish out,
当且仅当所有输入数据是正确的时候 方显数学的力量
but when all the data is correct, it's amazing what can be done with just the power of math.
在我们的现代世界 这种去能去火星的探测器
Our modern world and things like space probes to Mars
完全离不开数学上的精确计算
would just not be possible without someone doing the calculations.
后面是工商时间 感谢观看~
If you've ever wondered what it takes to calculate the route for a Martian probe
other guys over at brilliant.org can help you.
Brilliant is an interactive problem-solving website where you get to learn by solving real-world problems and think like a scientist or astronomist.
There are tons of problem-solving courses on things like gravitational physics that underpinned a motion of the planets
or you can try your hand at astronomy and do things like finding out the size of the universe
and if you're into rockets and stuff you can try classical mechanics to work out how things move around on earth and in space.
Sounds like rocket science? Well it is, but that doesn't mean the say has to be hard.
Brilliant do this by showing you problems and breaking them down into easy-to-understand steps
then putting them back together so you can see how the overall process works.
They also have a large active worldwide community ready and willing to help you along every step of a way so you're never alone.
To help support as a curiousdroid and to learn more about brilliant just click on the link to brilliant.org/curiousdroid and sign up for free.
As a special bonus for curious droid viewers, the first 200 people to sign up will get a 20% discount off of their annual subscription.